Welcome everybody to Introduction to Deep Learning. This is the second lecture and in this
lecture we're going to start with the machine learning basics. If we are remembering very
briefly from the previous lecture we gave a very high level overview of what this lecture content
is going to be and to be very precise I wanted to give a differentiation between AI, ML and DL,
artificial intelligence, machine learning and deep learning and what the differences are.
And this is exactly where we would like to continue today and specifically what we have
discussed was that artificial intelligence was pretty much anything we can write up in a program
even if statement you could in some way consider artificial intelligence and machine learning is
then the next well more sophisticated step where we have kind of a model that is being optimized
and is learning based on AI and DL. So let's get started.
So we have a model that is based on some training data in order to perform a certain task and then
finally we're going to talk about deep learning where we're going to have a neural network as
our model that is then well supposedly more powerful than alternative machine learning
methods. Okay and this is exactly where we would like to continue today and before we step into
these three categories again I would now have the orthogonal thing when we're talking about tasks.
So what I've just talked about was methods right what are learning methods, what are
artificial intelligence methods, algorithms and now we're going to talk about some tasks.
So mainly we want to apply these kind of methods that we have in these categories here.
We want to apply them for instance to computer vision and we would like to start with a very very
simple task here and a simple task could be image classification right. This is the task we're going
to deal with for quite a bit because it's very canonical and it's very practical for
computer vision applications. So what is it about?
It's relatively straightforward. So the task here is essentially give them a set of input images.
What we would like to do is we would like to assign a class label for each of these images
right. So each of these cats here we would like to assign an orange box and each of the dogs here
we would like to assign a blue box. And ideally the way we would like to do this is we have been
feeding this respective image that we want to look at and that we don't know the label yet.
We would like to make a prediction based
on a certain model that we're having for instance right. And this is the whole point of image
classification right. And the idea behind that is basically that we now in a sense having a mapping
from the input which is for instance a set of pixels to some form of output label right. So we
have to find a mapping from a bunch of pixels of this image to which output label is going to be.
And well you could you could imagine why this is becoming relatively complicated because the
diversity in natural images is actually quite complicated. To be a little bit more precise here
we see already that we have quite a high diversity here. But even these images that you see here just
for two simple classes for dogs and cats here you see that they're also relatively straightforward.
Meaning that in each of these images there's a unique label that can be associated to them.
Meaning that there's no mixture of like dogs and cats in the same image. So this is already
a much more simplified task than if you're considering like real world applications.
But even that simple task of image classification where it's a little bit easier. Even that one is
already pretty complicated and worth a look that we will devote quite a bit of time during this
lecture. But why is that even so complicated? And it's actually very straightforward if you're
looking at these images. So for instance if you take a very simple single project image here for instance, so this is one
instance if you're taking these kind of images here you see very briefly that we have a lot of
occlusions meaning that the problem that we're dealing with practically speaking here is that
the real world around us is actually in three dimensions but what the image is actually
portraying and visualizing is just based on two dimensions meaning we have kind of like
like the the camera that took this image took the 3d world and made it 2d and in this projection
the this is not a bijective mapping anymore right so we're losing some information from the 3d world
and we're going to 2d and because of that we can have many many 2d images for the same 3d objects
underneath right and this is a big problem meaning that the resulting well output here has things
like occlusions right so not all the dog here is always visible depending on from which camera
angle the image was taken and each of these images you can also see they have some stuff in it so
this image has a little box in it for example and this is a little box in it for example
so this image has a little box in it for example and this image has a little box in it for example
instance um and and so on so right so these occlusions make it very difficult adding more
complexity to the respective um yeah diversity of images we can also see that the backgrounds
can be vastly different right and this makes a big difference we can have very extreme cases
like these two here right so we can see here there's a white background with the white deck and
uh white dog in the foreground um and they have here a black cat during the night with
a black background right so this is kind of an extreme example why image classification
could become very tricky and why especially for computers it's very difficult to make distinctions
or to assign correct class labels in these specific cases here um and if you're just
continuing this what i've just talked about for instance you're going to you know just go in
google image search and you're trying to find for look for a bunch of cat images you see kind of a
large diversity um in terms of images um so you see very different poses how is the cat
looking what is the current pose like this is one this this kitten is kind of like in this up pose
here right um this cat here sitting down um this cat is like to the side so the cat itself can have
a different pose but also the camera what i just mentioned is because again we go from this 3d world
to the 2d image can also have a different pose right the camera pose here our camera parameters
can vastly change the camera in itself can also change by the way right so we can go ahead um and
have and connect the camera to the camera itself so we can go ahead and have and connect the camera
we can have different lenses we can have different focal lengths like simple autofocus or so might
actually change quite a bit how the image is going to look like um illumination can change um that's
very obvious right and illumination can be quite complicated right day night we have just seen
um but we can also have like vastly different environments basically where we see
um respectively different outputs and then of course we have different appearances with very
very extreme cases where like have a cat is kind of wrapped um like a
burrito and in that case of course it's very difficult to do a proper representation so if
you're summarizing most of these things um and a lot of people who have taken for instance computer
graphics courses they know basically the problem that we're dealing with here right so we're
basically dealing with the 3d world um we have a bunch of in graphics you would say scene parameters
right you have poses where the camera is located you're going to have light sources being
distributed in a scene you're going to apply some shading like
how do the respective materials reflect and so on so all the things that you feed in the graphics
pipeline they're going to tell you at the end of the day how an image is going to look like and as
i said this is not a bi-checked mapping meaning that there's many many images that actually
explain the same 3d underlying project uh object and even what makes matters worse even the 3d
shapes within one class are even diverse too so we have different 3d shapes and each 3d shape
can have different images associated to it and that problem
basically means that well this becomes a pretty difficult problem because for a bunch of like cats
we actually can have quite a large diversity of images and this makes image classification such a
challenging but also interesting problem that we would like to look at one of the key things that
we would also like to talk about in this lecture is what is the actual representation and this is
a really really big question um when i'm talking about classification um the representation for the
most part we're going to use
um as input is going to be a set of pixels it's a 2d array right we have rgb d values maybe probably
not d but most of the time we have rgb depth is not always given um sometimes it's just grayscale
sometimes rgb so these are typically our input representations that we're giving for instance
um when we're looking at a jpeg or a png file but then what we would like to do is we would like to
create higher level representations
and this is the thing we're going to talk a little about and we're going to talk about feature
extraction we would like to talk about representations that basically abstract all
these things away what i've just talked about right a good representation would be that all
of these different things here shouldn't matter for a good representation so this raw representation
of input pixels we would ideally like to map to some high level representation where it's much
easier to do classification um and this is something that we're going to use little networks
um but unfortunately there's still a few things we have to learn first we have to look at a few
things before we actually start with complicated feature learning um instead what we would like to
do is we would like to start a little bit simpler um in fact we would like to start very very soon
so the simplest possible way or the simplest let's say algorithm what we could deal with
um is a very simple classifier and the way what we could do here is
we could do simply nearest neighbor lookups so what does that mean well let's assume we're
having a bunch of images let's also assume um for these images we're going to have labels so
we know their respective classes right so for instance we have these images here uh for these
images we're having one two three four five six cat images we're going to label them with an
orange box this makes it clear that this is an orange box um that refers to cat uh we're going
to have two dogs here they have blue boxes
which is referring to a dog and now what we would like to do is we would consider these ones as our
reference images um reference images is is maybe not the right term the reason why I'm using it is
later we're going to call them training images but at the moment there's no training at the moment
all we would like to do is we would like to take these reference images here um and what we would
like to do is we would like to take a new image here and for this new image we would like to
understand
to
the closest hence the nearest neighbor so which of these other images is our nearest neighbor well
so how do we do that well it comes a little bit back to the question what we've addressed before
what is the right representation so in any kind of representation we would love to compute a distance
in other words what we would love to do is we would take this image and compare it against every
other image here right
right so let's just say we can do that let's just say we have this magic function right now
in how to make that comparison so we take this image compare it computer value this image that
image compare the value and so on and then what we're going to do is we're just going to go ahead
and sort all these images in our reference data set by these distances we just computed
um and we might end up getting something like this right so here we have our reference image
sorry here we have our query image and here we have all these reference images and now we're going
to have um a distance function to each of these ones we're going to get a distance value and we
sort this by distance so these things here this dog image is supposedly to be the closest and
these cat image here they're supposed to be the furthest distant away from this query image that
we have here right and the idea behind this nearest neighbor classifier is after we have computed the
distances
and after we have sorted them by the distance we simply assign the class level to the closest one
so in other words well okay this one is presumably the closest one uh and in this case our nearest
neighbor classifier would simply say well this is a dog right um and that's it now
um you might imagine of course there's a couple of drawbacks you might imagine it could be a large
data set there's a lot of compute involved but it could also be pretty noisy it might be accidentally
that there's like one image of a cat that looks surprisingly similar um and we would like to be
a little bit more robust so instead of saying oh I'm going to try to be the closest to this one dog
here or to this closest image I'm going to say I'm going to just take some sort of a median in
a sense right I'm going to go ahead and say I'm going to take the multiple nearest neighbors and
then simply do a majority vote which once is the majority in the k nearest neighbors so for instance
if we're saying we're setting this
k like this nearest neighbor classifier to a three-way nearest neighbor classifier so k nearest
neighbors where we said k to three um and we take the three closest images here one two three uh and
in this case we would say it's a cat actually right because now we have two images here that
are referring to a cat and um one image that refers to dog so our majority vote here told us
this is a cat of course this is wrong right in this case our
main nearest neighbor classifier was not that great uh but could you can imagine how this
basically changes right so you could imagine if we had a larger set of case we would get a little
bit more robust to the respective data right okay um what's kind of interesting is you can actually
go ahead and take this classifier um and plot it in 2D so in other words what we would love to do
uh we would simply take our data these are our reference images presumably
somehow um and now what we want to do is we want to assign like you want to kind of extrapolate we
want to make sure that the entirety of this 2D area here is going to be filled with associated
labels so no matter where you are in this 2D space you want to figure out what the respective nearest
neighbors are so if I'm here I'm taking the nearest point for instance this one then I
will assign a red here so this this point everything here is basically closest to this
one right everything here in this area is close to this red point and so on so this is just literally
the areas based on which reference image was the closest um and this is pretty straightforward all
you're doing is you're trying to find um the nearest neighbor point from where you are and
then you assign the respective class to where you are at the moment right and this of course
this changes now if you're going from a one nearest neighbor classifier to only taking the
nearest one to a five-way nearest neighbor classifier so from a five-way nearest neighbor
we are trying to figure out um which one like whether it's a little bit more robust so in this
case for instance there's a green point here right you see this so don't confuse my laser pointer
with point um because I have a red laser pointer but there's a green point here uh and here we
assign this one this area here was the closest to this green point and here since we're saying
we have five and nearest neighbor classifier um that means this this green point you get
ignored right so this outlier gets um gets ignored for the time being um and if you have
one outlier in our metric here that means our nearest neighbor classified gets slightly worse
not worse but it's um like here we're getting slightly better because we have five and be
ignoring it and supposed to be an outlet okay so let's have a bit of a discussion what the
implications are between one nearest neighbor five nearest neighbor and so on so let's have a couple
of um
um interesting questions so the first interesting question is well I called this previously the
reference data set in practice that's going to be our training data right uh in the end of the day
we want to train something on it um so if you're performing the nearest neighbor classifier on the
training data how would this perform on the training data right so this is kind of a trick
question because if we're trying to find the closest image and the current image that we're
querying is actually in the training data we would assume that the
query image finds the perfect reference image which finds itself right in the training in this
case you will assume that a nearest neighbor classifier would perform perfectly right it
would always find the right image and it would because it finds the right image it would also
assign the right class assuming of course our label is correct here we would make the correct
classification if you're taking a five and a nearest neighbor classifier that's always the case
right so these green points here these green points would not perform perfectly because they
would still be assigned to a red color meaning that they would get the wrong label and even
though they are performed on the training set they would not be perfect anymore so you can already see
that the nearest neighbor classifier and the 5nn classifier they they have slightly different
behavior and this is something we're going to later on pick up a little bit we'll be talking
about robustness in the context of neural networks like for instance how much do we want to regularize
how much we want to smooth the
labels and stuff like that this will become very relevant um the second question you want to ask
here is which classifier is likely to perform best on the test data well it depends right so
the one argument for having a larger K here is we are a little bit better with respect to outliers
and with respect to outliers means we actually have a better coverage of the training samples
and assuming our distribution is matching better between the training these reference
images that we had and the respective query image so in this case we would probably assume
that the the 5nn classifier would perform slightly better but there's a caveat I'm
going to give you an extreme example so if we are for instance setting our K equal to
the total number of images in the training set right um what that would mean is we always going
to take every image into account and just do a majority vote of all the images in our training
set and if that's the case we're just going to always predict the same label right so that's not
going to be very accurate in fact well it's going to just predict the majority class um and it's not
a great example so in this case like if you're choosing for instance this K too large that might
also be as loud downside so this is something also we have to consider and later on when we're doing
neural network optimization uh we can also follow the similar pitfalls here where we would accidentally
predict the majority class so this is always a good a good sanity check whenever we're doing
classifier training we want to do better than the majority class it's not just the average right if
you have more samples from one class we would have to figure out to be better than this one class please
to do anything um the next interesting question like what are we actually learning here right
remember we've talked about AI versus machine learning versus deep learning so if you want
to categorize our nearest neighbor classifier
um well so far if you're thinking carefully we haven't really done a lot of learning here right
there's no like parameters that are trained based on some training data and in fact we
we more or less hard-coded our training sets okay we do have a training set right
um but we didn't train any network here right um or we didn't train any model in this case
and in practice we just hard-coded our samples and we tried to assign it
um and hard-coded in our decision criteria right so which one is closer and based on that we made
a decision so there's no actual learning in a sense going on right um however there's a few
things we can actually play around with um and these things are some hyper parameters
um and higher parameters is a term if you haven't heard it um that's a term that we're going to
mention a lot these are basically parameters that are not part of our model in this case we don't
have a model so there's no other
parameters and these are parameters that are choices for the algorithm itself okay so for
instance in this case hyper parameters is something like which distance function we're going to choose
so the simplest distance function we could choose for our nearest neighbor classifier could be an
L1 distance right so we're just going to take um the pixel values we're going to compare them
one by one and we're going to just compute an L1 distance between the r2p values and that's
going to give us the distance
uh we can also do the same thing with an L2P
we can also do the same thing with an L2P
distance we can choose and decide depending on how we feel like and what we feel works better
and to get different distance function and based on the distance function you
hopefully can also change the outcome and the behavior of our respective classifier
we can also change the number of neighbors right so this k as we have noticed is quite
um quite important um and and this is kind of the the typically higher parameters we would get
in a nearest neighbor classifier now these parameters they are very problem dependent right
so we don't know right depends on what kind of classifier we have what data set we have
we would like to change these ones and now you can already see well now there's
a bit of a concept of learning coming into play right
and by learning
coming into play means well now we would like to look at our data set in this case our training
data set or our reference data set what i called it before um and would like to learn or adjust
these parameters to a certain level um so the big question is how do we actually choose these
hyper parameters right um and now machine learning comes into play right now we want to move from
a nearest neighbor classifier to using machine learning methods in order to learn these classes
okay now what we do here is we would like to perform image classification right so in this
case we have our task we've just defined that one and when we're doing machine learning here we
would like to take a bunch of data experiences we would like to take these ones and we would
like to learn from these ones to learn a model and i'm trying to formalize this a little bit so don't
be too nitpicky here in the formulation um this formulation will not be consistent with the rest of
the model but the high level concept is always going to be the same for every machine learning
for every machine learning problem and again this is a classifier right now but the high level
concept of you having a a certain model you want to find parameters for that model and for the
input you want to make a certain prediction so i want to make clear what i mean by this okay so
here's our model so this is our model m here this model m here has a bunch of parameters
it takes an images input
and it makes a class label prediction right like i'm not going to go into detail like
how the class labels are being encoded right now or how the images are encoded
i wanted to go a step back right make this very high level just get the high level concept of
machine learning and if you know machine learning already i'm sure this is really a good repetition
because this is really a concept that is always going to be shared across many families of
machine learning methods right okay um so yeah so what we have is we have the model m right we have
parameters theta we have an input image i and we have two output labels class labels dog or cat
note i'm not having any hybrid parameters here this theta these are the model parameters this
is very different from the hybrid parameters and we'll later see exactly what that means
but practically as i said the model parameters they're being optimized on the training set
and the hybrid parameters this is a sign choice on the algorithm itself
how we do for instance optimization of these parameters or how big our model is going to be
so we have a lot of hybrid parameters but now what we would love to do is we would like to figure out
if you're taking a bunch of images um we would like to make sure that our model in some sense
follows these predictions what these images have been annotated so in other words if i have a lot
of images um and these images here for this image is the dog if i'm feeding this image i here um this
dog image
here when i feed this image in i would like to make it a dog prediction on the other hand if
i feed this cat image in i would like to make it a cat prediction and now the whole point of machine
learning is that we're starting with a data set like this one and now what we're doing is we're
taking a part of these images um and i've already mentioned it a couple of times because i'm so
used to it um so these images this part of these images we're going to call the train set so we're
going to take given these eye images with training labels so these are the images we're going to start
some training and we would like to do is we would like to make sure that our model makes these
predictions that is in the trendset and then what we're hoping is assuming we have we have figured
out our model based on these images that our model also makes correct predictions on previously
unseen images so if i'm training on these ones i hope that the model makes also good
predictions on these ones ideally perfect predictions right so
this is our training uh train set here and this is something we're going to call the validation set
and the way this is going to go is when i say training
for the most part and again don't go too much into my notation here i just wanted to make this
very very dead simple um what we're going to do is we're going to find these parameters data
and in this case what we do here is we optimizing for a theta such that um
we're going to have a data set here that's going to make the prediction of the model
and what this prediction looks like so if we sum over our training images
our model here if we're summing over all of our training images
minimize the distance between the labels and what the model predicts so model predictions
and ground truth labels these are the ground truth labels cat dog and dog
these ones should match right so if i feel an image i i want to make the label prediction of this image i
function. There's a lot of different ways how to define these distance functions. We're going to
talk about a couple of these ones today and presumably going to talk about a couple of more
in the next lectures as well. Another question is how are these labels even defined? Are these
literally numbers like 0 and 1? There could be also a couple of different ways how to define
those numbers. And then how is the image I define? I mean pixels is the obvious one but could be also
all the things. But the high level concept between machine learning is always going to be the same.
It's always very similar. So what you're doing is you're having some form of a training set.
You're taking these labels here in the ground truth labels and you're trying to make sure the
model predicts whatever the ground truth labels are. This is what you want to do. And then what
I just mentioned a couple of times, I mentioned this concept of training. Well this is also when
I'm making a model, I'm going to be making a model that's going to be able to predict the
ground truth labels. So what I'm going to be doing is I'm going to be making a model that's going to
be able to predict the ground truth labels. So what I'm going to be doing is I'm going to be
mentioning training. For the most part what I mean is I mean run your favorite optimization
to find the optimal parameters theta prime such that this model best fits this training set,
right? This is what we want to do. We would like to make sure that our model fits the training set,
explains the labels in the training set. And once we've trained that model, meaning we have tried
to find an optimal solution based on the training set such this model approximates the distance
distribution of these labels here, we hope that our model eventually generalizes. And
generalization means now if I feed in unseen images that we also make reasonable predictions.
Now I mentioned a lot of terms here. I mentioned the concept of training set. I mentioned the
concept of training versus optimization. I mentioned hyperparameters and model parameters.
And I mentioned this concept of generalization. When we like going from a training set where we're
using these ones as constraints and the optimization to train our model versus
predicting and generalizing to unseen observations or to unseen samples, you know, right?
Okay. So if you're trying to go and make this even more abstract, the basic concept of machine
learning follows is mainly data driven. So most, well, pretty much all machine learning methods
come to mind. They all in some way data driven. So when I'm going to talk about machine learning,
I always mean there's some data and based on this data, you're going to train a model. And based on
this model, you're going to make predictions on things that you haven't seen before. Okay. So what
we do first is whenever we develop an algorithm and what we do have in computer vision is for
instance, an image data set, right? Like ImageNet is a great example. That's widely used. So what
we do is we're splitting our data. We're having a train data set. We're having a validation data set
and a test data set.
And what we do here is we say, for instance, we have a split like 60, 20, 20%, right? So this is
100% of our data. We're splitting it up in order to develop our algorithm. And what we would love
to do here is we would like to take our training set. Basically all in the past, what I've told
you in the previous slides is mostly start with the training set. And what we want to do is we
want to find model parameters theta based on the training. What does it mean finding model parameters?
Well, model parameters means we're running an optimization. The training samples are given us
constraints for this optimization. And we're basically running this, this optimization, right?
So based on our distance function, we're trying to find optimal theta prime parameters that give
us good answers. Now, if you're going further, now we have our validation set. You might ask,
well, why on earth do we need a validation and a test set? Can I just train these model parameters
and go make some predictions on having some accuracy or so on my classifier? And I'm going to
be done.
You could do that. However, the problem is assuming you're running your training set,
you're having a bunch of model parameters theta, you want to evaluate how well your model is doing.
So now I'm going to go ahead and going to evaluate my model, how well it's doing. And I'm realizing,
yeah, okay, it's not that great. I would like to change a few things. So for instance,
if I go back quickly, I would like to change this distance function d. I would like to change
the different one. If you did this, this would mean you're changing a hyperparameter here.
And you're training again, and then you're getting a different result, right? So you might say,
well, okay, I'm getting different results when I change some of these hyperparameters.
That's kind of logical. But now you have to re-evaluate again, right? And in this case,
when you're re-evaluating again, you're going to get different results.
So the important thing right now is basically when you are finding hyperparameters,
you want to use the validation set, meaning that you can do this multiple times and you can go ahead and
train, evaluate, change a bunch of parameters, train again, evaluate again, and so on.
So you can do this pretty much as much as you want. And in practice, you would do this as much as you want,
because this is quite important, because you're going to realize some of your models might have certain weaknesses.
Some of your loss functions might not be ideal. Some of your regularizers, we'll talk about this also later,
what that means. Some of your optimization parameters might have been not ideal.
And you might have to change certain things. And if you did this,
that would mean you're looking actually at the results.
So in other words, as soon as you're doing that, you're not looking at the real data anymore,
because as soon as you're considering the validation samples,
you're actually taking those ones as part of your model development, as your model training process.
And because of that, we now need a separate test set that is actually different from the validation set.
And the key critical part here,
is once we found our right hyperparameters, once we're happy with our model choices,
once we're happy with how the model trains and how it evaluates on the validation set,
only then we can go ahead and test on the test set.
And this is really important.
And a lot of people get it wrong, even in the research community.
The important thing is that you only test once.
So as soon as you go ahead and test multiple times, in a sense, you're cheating.
Why are you cheating? Because now you're taking test information from samples where you would like to understand
how well your model channelizes to, you're using that information how to train your model.
And this is really critical.
And I can give you a couple of examples how this could actually work in practice.
So in the research community, typically what happens, there's data sets available.
Computer vision, right? And these data sets, they're going to give you certain results.
So now the problem is, of course,
if you want to objectively evaluate, you want to make sure that,
you know, you have a test set that people don't use over and over again.
Because if people always use their test sets and they're trying so many times while developing the algorithm
and trying all the time on the test set, eventually they're just doing whatever's in the test set, right?
And they will find parameters that give the best test performance.
But they're cheating. They shouldn't have used the test set for that purpose.
In fact, they should have used the validation set and then try to see how well it channelizes to unseen samples
they did not consider doing in their method.
And in practice, what people do then in computer vision often is they have benchmarks.
And benchmark often means that people give out,
for instance, test images and then people have to run the algorithms on the test images
and then they upload their results to an evaluation server.
But the catch is the test image labels are not given to the respective users.
So they don't know what they're doing, basically.
So they're only going to get once a result back from the test image.
Now, you could imagine that people are trying
to get around this. People try to make multiple accounts on these benchmark servers and stuff like this.
But now you can guess, well, this is suddenly a point of cheating
where you're basically not reflecting the channelization to real data anymore.
So this is a very, very important concept.
OK, so bottom line here is use training to optimize the model parameters,
use the validation to find the hyperparameters, iterate as many times as you want.
And until you're happy with that,
then you test at the very end of the day, you test on the test.
Now, if you're going back to our task,
how can we learn now to perform image classification?
Well, we have two things right now. We have a task.
We have image classification. We have experience.
That's our training and validation data.
And now what we do is we have some performance measure that is giving us some accuracy.
And this is typically what we evaluate at the end of the day of the test set.
And then we have a metric that tells us how well does
our method actually work in practice.
Great. So this is the very high level concept of machine learning.
And now if you're asking, well,
why are there so many different machine learning methods?
Well, the question is always how does this model look like
and how do we optimize it and fit it to the respective training data?
How do we make it channelized very well?
And the reason why we're having this lecture
and the reason why it enjoys a lot of popularity right now is that the networks,
neural networks, they perform very well as these models.
And we can show later on that they have great channelization for many, many, many tasks.
OK, so before we get actually into simple machine learning models,
I would like to have a few things that I would like to clarify.
So what I've just described as machine learning for the most part was supervised machine learning.
However, I would also like to acknowledge and I would like to say, well,
there's also unsupervised machine learning.
And I would like to make it a quick differentiation between those
because a lot of people, of course, have heard about these two terminologies
and it's very important to distinguish between those.
So when we're talking about supervised learning,
we always mean we have some labels given, target classes, some regression targets and so on.
And what we'd like to do is we have a training set here.
We have these labels, for instance, here, and we would like to train a model based
on the data such that ideally it matches the distribution
and then channelizes to an unseen set of samples at the end of the day.
Now, here's the challenge.
For the most part of this course, we're going to deal with supervised learning.
There's going to be a few exceptions where we deal with unsupervised learning.
For the most part, I would say 90 plus percent of this course,
we're going to deal with supervised learning.
And when I'm going to talk about machine learning, in the context of this course,
for the most part,
I'm going to refer to supervised learning.
But this is, of course, not true.
There's unsupervised learning.
There's also things like self-supervised learning and so on.
I want to give you a few examples here.
So unsupervised learning is basically when you don't have class labels,
when you don't have any labels, basically.
And the idea of unsupervised learning is, for the most part,
some form of clustering of the structure, right?
So you try to figure out, essentially, so let's say you have the data
and you're trying to divide your samples into clusters
and then you assign a class label to each cluster.
So this class label doesn't necessarily have a semantic meaning,
but it just assigns a class label to it.
And based on the class label, you can then finally, well,
make some use of it in one way or another.
And in that case, what we would do is to say,
okay, here we have, for instance, our example of our cats and dogs again.
Let's say we can cluster them.
Let's say we can cluster those ones into two classes.
Unsupervised learning here would say, well, okay, you have these two classes,
you assign labels, but technically speaking,
you don't know any semantic labels yet unless somebody goes manually
and assigns cluster labels what we've gotten out of it.
There's also a lot of unsupervised learning in the context of deep learning.
It does exist, and we will talk a little bit about it.
But for the most part, the focus of this class will not necessarily,
of course, will not necessarily be on unsupervised learning.
There's also a very fun discussion of what is the more natural thing,
like unsupervised learning versus supervised learning.
It's very philosophical, and researchers in the last decades have gone back and forth.
There's a fun argument, a very philosophical one, is have humans,
do we learn supervised or do we learn unsupervised?
And the fun argument is, well, at the beginning when there was no life on Earth,
eventually,
like humanity, life in general, had to start learning somehow, right?
And then basically the argument is everything can be learned in the unsupervised fashion.
And then the cognitive argument is that is, well, if you have some,
if you don't listen to a language, for instance, as a child,
you're not being able to speak very well.
And you can only do this very well when somebody corrects you,
when somebody tells you certain things.
And a lot of the things your parents do with you
when a kid is actually quite supervised.
And I found this very interesting.
So I'm obviously,
I know I don't understand the biology behind how your brain works here.
But I think it's kind of interesting,
the debate versus like how much supervision do we actually need for learning?
It's a very fun, fun question to ask
when we're talking about modern machine learning techniques,
specifically in the context of representation learning.
A lot of people say, well, you have a large number of labels.
Is there a large number of training samples on the internet,
for instance, where you don't have labels,
but can you still use the data and then combine it later on with some fine tuning?
Where you do actually have labels.
So this is kind of interesting, a lot of cool stuff.
But again, caveat here for the introduction to deep learning here,
we are mostly talking about supervised learning.
I also wanted to mention that there's reinforcement learning.
That's, I guess, kind of in between here.
Reinforcement learning has kind of this interesting concept of agents and environment, right?
So agents interact with an environment and based on their performance,
they're going to get some reward.
And depending on how this reward goes,
your agent is going to adapt and hopefully learn something, right?
So, for instance, in games, board games or even video games,
for instance, reinforcement learning is very popular.
Robotics reinforcement learning is very popular,
where you basically have only a final reward.
And based on that final reward, your model can learn something
and can, for instance, learn certain policies,
like, I don't know, playing chess or learning how to play a video game,
which is kind of cool that you can do this in a kind of,
well, unsupervised fashion.
But I would say this is still a little bit in between
because you still need to define how the reward works.
You still need to define basically when you're winning,
when you're losing, possibly how much you're winning,
how much you're losing.
So it's kind of an interesting question,
how to associate reinforcement learning.
Okay, but let's go back to supervised learning.
I mentioned this is what we would love to talk about for the most part here.
And now,
if we're going back a few slides mentally,
we remember that the whole point of supervised learning was we have our training set
and we would like to figure out a model that we fit to this training set, right?
So again, we have our model M, for instance.
We would like to find parameters theta such that our model approximates
or mimics the distribution of this training set.
Now, the big question is what model do we actually use?
Well, let's start with a simple linear model, for instance, right?
And that's the easiest way of a model we could think about.
So this is a linear decision boundary that we would like to figure out.
So the idea here is we would like to fit a hyperplane
that splits our samples in part here for a classifier.
For regression, it's a little bit different.
We can do a little bit other stuff.
But if you had a classifier, we would like to have a hyperplane.
We would like to split these two things apart.
And this is what we're going to do right now.
So all we're going to do in the next few slides
is we're trying to find parameters for this hyperplane
that figures out how to approximate our training set to the best of our abilities.
And you can already see why I'm saying approximate.
I'm saying this for a very specific reason,
because you can clearly see the common here of a linear model here
is that it cannot possibly
fit all data samples, right?
So if you had one of these triangles, if you had one of them here,
there would be no hyperplane possible anymore to fit in here,
such that it perfectly explains the training set.
And that would be a problem.
So why am I starting with it?
And that's basically the pro. The pro is, well,
it's really simple to understand how basic machine learning works.
And it's probably the simplest model we can begin with.
But it also has certain advantages in practice.
It's actually relatively easy to deploy.
It doesn't take that much, can, right?
It doesn't have so many degrees of freedom.
And it's actually a very nice way to get into it.
So let's start with it.
So now instead of starting with a classifier,
I would like to change the problem statement a little bit.
In this case, we want to start with regression.
And instead of the classifier,
the difference here is when I talk about regression,
it's simply you, instead of predicting a discrete label,
we're now predicting a continuous floating point.
So if we want to do this,
we would like to use this as our output for instance.
And the idea of supervised learning now is, well,
we would like to find a linear model that explains a target Y
given the inputs X.
Well, okay.
So what do we have here?
Well, we're going to start with our training data.
These points here, they are now our training data.
So these red points, right?
They have, they have an X value.
They have a Y value.
So the X values are the inputs.
so
That's what we'd like to approximate. We would like to make sure that this distribution that is given right now for these given inputs
We would like to make sure that if we give importance to this input feature here
Because I shouldn't call it a feature here
I should call it first like a value here for this value here. We like to make the Y value here as a prediction and
The way what linear regression is doing. It's essentially fitting this this little line here
right
and
This fitting this line and I'm mentioning this all the time fitting means which is literally formulating an optimization function here
Is we are optimizing the parameters of this line?
This will become a higher plane obviously later when we go to higher dimensions, but for 2D this is just a simple line
Okay
So what's training mean? Well training means we have a bunch of data points given so data points are these these yellow or orange points
right
These orange points
They are pairs. They have an input
And a target so they have X is the respective like feature. This is the input
This is the measurement could be an image and Y is the respective target label right so
input image
measurement whatsoever and
Y is our respective labels like cat-dog and the classification case or in the regression case
We'll see later a few other examples. It could be could be discrete, right? It could be also continuous. By the way, if you're going to click it back here
um
At the moment, between regression and classification, there's practically no difference.
We'll later see what the differences are.
But the reason for the simplicity right now, let's just assume these labels are continuous.
So if they're classified, we just say, oh, these labels are between 0 and 1, right?
And you're going to make sure that everything between 0.5, then it's label 1.
Everything under 0.5 is going to be label 0, right?
But it could be continuous label 2, right?
Okay.
So we have input measures.
We have labels.
And what we would like to do is we would like to learn the model parameters theta to make the correct estimation.
And what does correct estimation mean?
Well, we would like to make sure that y hat is, if I feed in a new x n plus 1 here, we get a correct estimation y hat.
And you can see what's very important here.
So this notation is important.
We're going to use this a bit.
So x is always the input.
Y is always the target.
So this is our ground truth target.
Y hat is always going to be our predicted estimation.
This is what the model predicts.
X n plus 1, you see n plus 1 here is one index more than what we have in the training set.
This is a test sample here.
So we're feeding this in here in our model.
Theta is our model parameters.
And based on theta, we have.
We're having a predictor that makes this prediction here, right?
And the whole point is that we want to find these parameters theta.
Again, to clarify, this can be the parameters of a neural network.
This concept here does not change right now.
Like the only point right now is going to be whether this theta is part of a linear or nonlinear larger model.
But for the sake of simplicity, we're not quite at neural networks yet.
We're going to make this a little bit easier.
This theta here is now simply a linear model.
And linear model means.
It's linear.
That's the definition.
So what we do here right now is.
We're taking the input here.
So X here is the input.
And we're multiplying with theta.
So imagine this little example that we had here.
I'm going to go quickly back.
In this case, if X is just a single floating point value.
And it's just one scalar.
Then this here.
This D here.
This is the input dimension.
Would be one.
So we just have.
A single theta multiplied with X.
That's it.
And you're predicting Y.
And then you're finding whatever our respective output is going to be approximated best.
Now, in practice, this is a little bit more complicated.
This is the features.
This is why I mentioned this already.
X is not just a single scalar.
X could actually be a vector, right?
There could be many, many, many inputs.
An image is a very large feature, for instance, right?
An image could be like a megapixel, a million pixels, right?
Could be a lot of.
Could be a lot of pixels.
Could be a lot of inputs.
So, and D here is our dimension.
So, oh, I'm not here yet.
Sorry.
These are the weights.
Then these are the model parameters, the theta here.
And D is our input dimension, right?
And again, think about the example, what I just mentioned before.
In this example, if I only have a single dimension, here's input.
I just have an X here.
And I want to fit a plane to it.
Oh, in one day.
Actually.
I want to just fit in this line.
Now I'm cheating a little bit here.
This is technically a little bit wrong for my formulation.
If you go into the 1D case, you will quickly notice this.
You also need a bias here.
So you need, um, you need a theta zero.
Um, why do you need that?
Well, technically you don't need it, but I think it makes the fitting a little bit easier.
So technically you need, um, where the, uh, line here intersects with the Y axis, right?
Um, and this one is important.
Because otherwise you cannot define arbitrary lines.
Otherwise they would only go, uh, through zero, zero, and you would just literally define the slope here, right?
But we have the slope and we have, um, uh, we have basically where, uh, the line intersects with the Y axis here.
Okay.
And, but then the rest is the same, right?
So we have here the bias plus the formula we just had, right?
We just say we multiply X, I, J with theta chain, right?
Input feature dimension plus with the kernel.
And then we just multiply it out, and this is essentially what we're getting from our sum here, right?
Okay.
Um, I think let's have an example, right?
This is actually relatively easy.
So this shouldn't be something new to you from a mathematical perspective.
So all we're trying to have is we have a certain set of constraints.
Our constraints are given by our data points, these orange points here.
Um, and what we would like to do is.
We would like to make sure that the thetas are optimized such that these points here are approximated in the best possible way, best possible way is also something we'll define in a second, because depending on our loss function.
Okay.
Let's make a linear prediction.
Let's predict the temperature of a room.
Let's assume we want to make sure, um, I'm going to give you a bunch of information and I would like to ask you, what is the temperature of a building?
Well, what information could I give you?
And this is.
The features that I'm giving you right now.
So I'm going to give you four different type of features here.
I'm going to tell you how warm it is outside.
I'm going to tell you the level of humidity.
I'm going to tell you the number of people in the building, and I'm going to tell you the sun exposure to the building, right?
Okay.
And now what I would like to do is I would like to, I would like to ask you based on these inputs that you have, what is the most likely temperature of the inside of the building?
So give me a model.
The dust that, um, and in order to do that, what I'm, what I'm, what I'm giving you also is I'm going to give you a bunch of supervision.
So I'm going to give you a bunch of ground truth pairs for training, where I pair these four dimensional input features here with our respective prediction.
Right.
Okay.
And that's what we're going to do.
Um, so this is a trick question now, how many parameters do we need to fit that?
Well, we're taking this formula that we had before each of these features is associated from data, right?
So all we're doing right now is just rebating how each of these features contribute to the input or to, to the output temperature of the building.
Right.
Um, and we have a bias, of course, so we have one more.
Um, so we have this, um, and now what we can do is we can write this down as a matrix form, right?
Uh, so now what we do is we just hit, um, here, we're going to have the respective prediction of our model here.
We're going to have the respective thetas.
Um, and here we're going to have the respective, um, input features that we have.
So this D here in our case, this one was four, right?
Um, so this one went from one to four.
Um, and this N here is how many measures we have, like the number of rows in this equation tells us how many samples we have and the number of, sorry, the number of columns tells us, um, how many features we have and the number of rows.
Um, tells us how many samples we have, right?
Okay.
And the idea is that if we, now we can pull this, this bias actually in here, right?
So we just having, we're just combining this matrix here.
So we're just adding, um, another column with ones here.
So we end with theta zero here now, uh, and we can just simply write this as a matrix form.
So now what we know is Y hat is equal to X times theta.
And now it's important what we have here.
Y is a vector, X is a matrix and theta is also a vector.
Theta is in fact our unknown vector, which is the most important thing we'd want to figure out this one right now.
Um, well, that's what we'd like to figure out.
Okay.
Um, so this is a linear equation system, right?
Um, what you would know from, from, um, analysis and algebra.
Um, so linear algebra tells you that depending on how many unknowns you have, you need a certain number of equations.
Right?
So what might happen here is your equations might, so your system here might be overdetermined, undetermined, or fully determined, right?
So if the thetas and the number of samples are the same, this is going to be a, uh, this here is going to be a square matrix, right?
Um, sorry, this here is also, this here is going to be a square matrix too, of course then, um, and then we can, can have a unique solution where we have the best fit possible.
If we have two.
Okay.
More of them.
Well, then we have to find a different way, or if you have a few of them, we also have to find a different way.
And little spoiler, what I'm practically going to do is we're going to do a least squares fit.
Um, okay.
So let's make this more concrete again.
I want to, I want to make sure that everybody gets this, because this is very fundamental for what we're going to do with the neural networks, because neural networks are not so far away from this, what we're doing here right now.
So in fact, this here, we have the predictions of our model.
So the y hat one to y hat n.
Uh, we're going to have the model parameters.
Which we have here, theta zero to theta d.
This is the dimension here.
Um, we also know, um, the input feature dimensionality, right?
Obviously what feature dimensionality plus one needs to match with the number of, um, parameters in our model.
Otherwise this like a row times calling multiplication doesn't work anymore.
Um, and yeah, and then what we need to know now is, well, we have these input features one.
Sample here has D features or D dimensional feature, and you could call the whole thing one feature as well.
And it's a feature vector then.
Um, and then we have our model respectively.
Okay.
So let's make it more concrete in our example.
So our example was our temperature in the building.
So what do we have here?
We have the, the T this one was the bias at the beginning.
Um, we have the outside temperature.
We have humidity, number of people and sun exposure.
That's seven percent, right?
Um, so now what we want to do is we want to figure out how can we train our model?
Well, our model right now has 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 parameters.
So for these parameters are directly associated with the respective input features.
And one of them is the bias.
So if, for instance, one of these.
entries here zero that means this info feature will be ignored right if there's a zero then this
feature will not contribute to the output predictions um if this one has a very high
value then this feature will contribute a lot and what's also interesting is assuming for instance
the sun exposure here is in percent assuming i didn't write the percentage in integers and i
would divide it by 100 well ideally our model would figure out um that you just have to divide
the model parameters here also by 100 right so otherwise you would actually change the result
so in principle the scaling and stuff like this should factor out because if you multiply this
one you should just divide this one respectively right and so on okay but it is very straightforward
right so we have here our uh our our our made up samples that we have so we have two samples here
that we are making up uh these are our made up things um if you're having two samples we
uh know already that we are under constraint right so we have two predictions for these two samples
um
but we have our model so if we have the model already what can we do here for this model we
can make certain predictions so if we have these input features and these input features our model
will make certain predictions here right so if you're running this through the model this one
would mean oh this one uh is great this is warm and this one would mean oh no it's cold
i didn't do the multiplication here but i assume this is a larger number and this one
i assume is a smaller number okay um but now the big question is so this is a
so this is a larger number okay so this is a larger number okay so let's assume we have these model
let's assume we have these model parameters here but now the question in the learning process is
how do we actually obtain these model parameters and i mentioned it a couple of times this leads to
linearly squares optimization so we have to figure out how can we find these parameters
how can we solve these equation systems okay how do we do it well we have the data points x here
uh these data points x they give you give us our model parameters
so they're being fed into the model parameters based on these ones we're making an estimation
um we have here our ground truth we're defining a loss function here and based on that loss
function we're updating the model parameters again right and then we optimize right um and that's
what we're going to do data points is input model parameters estimation loss function how wrong are
we and then we optimize okay so what are the two important things here we have introduced two two
important concepts here so the concept here is we have the loss function that measures the loss of
how good is my estimate and tell the optimization how to make it better right so how good's my model
and how do i make it better like what is how to make it better mean well the idea for the loss
function is it should get smaller and the model gets better right if the loss function is high or
if the loss is high um then we know our model is not that great and we have to change something so
if i change something my loss goes down but i'm like yeah i've been great and the optimization it
changed the model in order to improve the loss function right so i want to improve the estimations
based on my training samples that i have available and again this concept here is the same across all
of machine learning very much okay maybe there's certain things that do slightly differently but
this high level concept is we have a loss function we want to minimize it we want to optimize it and
based on the optimization we want to change the model in order to improve the loss function right
so how do we do with this in the context of the linear regression well again i'm
reiterating here we have to solve our linear uh least square system so we have this prediction
of the temperature in the building um and this optimization process pretty much goes like that
right so what i'm going to do is i'm going to going to have this line here i'm going to check
my distance i'm going to see huh all right this gives me a certain value uh now i have another
value that is up there and if the value is up there and tells me oh no there's a high loss here
i have to
to change my line right so i have to update i have to update this line such that the overall
average loss actually goes down this is what this loss function is going to do right and i'm trying
to use an average and treating all samples equally right now we'll later talk about what we do with
these outliers because that's obviously a bad case but this is what we would like to address okay
um well what we do okay so we mentioned we have to solve our famous linear least squares problem
right
so what we do is we just take an l2 loss um we compare our predictions with the respective
ground truth samples um and we're trying to minimize that that that function right so
that's all we're going to do so also what you'll see a lot of people will call this function very
differently some people call it objective objective function energy cost function and so on
all the same stuff right just depending who you're gonna ask if it's a math guy a machine learning guy
and so on
okay so how do we do that well we have to optimize for that
um and now we have to minimize that function so minimization here means minimize
this function here in order to fit the linear model to the respective data points that's what
we care about right now right okay this is actually a convex problem
meaning that there is actually a closed form solution solution that is unique um and of course
linear algebra tells you exactly how to do that um and if you're doing this the way this is done
is we're doing this over all the training samples so we have n training samples here
so we're taking the average so we'll be dividing by n here um and the important
thing right now here is that this y hat we have to express actually with our respective model
all right so our respective model like you might be surprised so why on earth what is he talking
about like there's a theta here um but there's no theta here anymore okay um so this y hat is
nothing else but xi times theta uh this is the estimation from the linear model this is the
linear model what it's doing uh and note that this is extremely matrix notation here right already
right so this one here is going over the training samples but this one here is one feature vector
times our vector of weights and this is a a vector this is a dot product here right
and this dot product because there's another sum here we can now go ahead and write write the whole
thing as a matrix notation right so we can write this square thing as the matrix notation um in
this case we know this one is now a matrix this is n training samples each has an input vector of
of d and this x here is written as a matrix basically all right so these
are our training samples here and here um and of course i'm assuming you know also this function
this is nothing else but the normal equation it's the same thing um and we also know that this y here
is our n label that we care about right so these ones we want to approximate this is a matrix this
is a vector this is also a vector right um we will talk a little bit about the matrix notation in the
exercise session um we understand a lot of people taking this lecture um well let's put it this way
the linear algebra course might have been a few semesters ago and we're happy to give a bit of a
refresher course here so you want to keep this course relatively easy to follow so we are actually
giving you um a bit of an intro on the matrix notation so if you were a bit struggling here
i would recommend maybe pause the video here and actually go and and check our our tutorial on the
matrix notation first um however at the same time for the rest of the sake of the video i'm assuming
that you know or at least have a basic
knowledge of the matrix notation so i'm assuming that you know or at least have a basic knowledge
of matrix notations okay all right so what does it mean well this is obviously a convex function
um this is the normal equation right um we know that from linear algebra um and we know that
there's an optimum and we know how to find the optimum and the way how we do find that optimum
is very straightforward um actually we have learned this already in high school in high
school we know if we have a quadratic function like this one this is a quadratic function it's
the normal equation um then we know that the gradient um
when the gradient is zero here we know that we have found a minimum or a maximum depending on
what shape the function is right but we have an extrema when the gradient is going to be zero
so how do we optimize that well um it's also relatively straightforward we just compute the
gradient of this matrix form right and if you're taking the gradient with respect to the thetas
that's what we care about these are our parameters we would like to solve for we end up with two times
x times theta minus two times x transpose times y and this should be equal to zero right this is
all constrained here so we're saying please find me the gradient with a finding point with the
gradient zero that's what we're setting here and the way we're finding that is it's xt times x
inverse times xty right and again you will notice this very rightfully this is this is the normal
equation right like if you if you bring this one here to the other side then you have xt times
x times theta is equal to xt times y which is our residual this is nothing else but a linear system
to solve right um there's a lot of a lot of things um i would love to give maybe a bit of
more intro on the algebra um this is the thing that i i unfortunately still experience even at
the phd level that people often struggling is how to solve systems like these ones right
um this is something that is very important like how do you even remember a matrix like this right
so in practice once you would never invert a matrix like this you would always use a linear
solver library especially when the matrix becomes large um there will be details in the exercise
session so again please look into this when you have any struggling with that i know there's a
bit of redundancy that's why i moved a little bit of stuff out here um to the exercise sessions and
i hope that you can catch up with the things you might have forgotten about linear algebra
okay um but assuming we can do that right we have found an
easy solution to a complex problem um what do we do here again well the inputs here are
our features like outside temperature number of people humidity um and on and this here on the
right hand side is our true output it's the temperature of the building and this is a least
squares estimate right um so there's this is not necessarily the best estimate but this is the
simplest estimate this is why we started
with this one um and there's a couple of different estimators here we're going to go through
um and each estimator has different properties right so for instance one thing what we have seen
here if you're taking a square term here you will see that if we're having one outlier in this least
squared estimate we will unfortunately have a bit of a problem because if we have one outlier
then unfortunately um yeah we might not be very robust to these outliers so for instance if you're
taking an l1
loss here instead of an l2 loss um then we might be a little bit more robust to outliers
unfortunately optimization becomes a little bit more tricky right so again also i hope that most
people know that i'm still going to repeat it a couple of times right if you're having an l2 loss
here it's a least squares estimate the optimum will always be the mean and if you have one
outlier the mean will shift quite a bit if you have an l1 loss for instance here the optimum
here will be the median and then if you have one outlier that will not affect the result that much
okay all right so let's talk a little bit more so this is basically an estimate we have done
based on an least square estimate now what i would like to do is i would like to talk about this
from a probabilistic standpoint and and this is a thing called maximum likelihood so it's very much
related um and we want to show why it's related um to our linear regression that we have just seen
so maximum likelihood is also a concept
you might have heard in your stochastic lectures already um but the core idea here is very specific
to machine learning meaning that what we would love to do is we would like to love to look at
some data um and this data has a certain distribution right so it might be a sequence of
numbers it might be a bunch of images it might be language right there's a true distribution right
um so given samples
this is basically
our true distribution here this is our data what we have right so we have here our uh what is our
respective value conditioned on the respective input right that's what we care about this is
what's in our data that's our true distribution that we would care about um and then what we have
is we have our model now our model we would like to mimic our data to some degree and i'm going
to talk about what this means by mimic it um so let's assume our model here is a parametric family
of distributions right so how is it parameterized well this is these these data parameters that's
what we've been talking about all the time right now right so these data parameters they are model
parameters what we would like to do is that these theta parameters make sure that our model right
now here um approximates basically our respective distribution and what a maximum likelihood
estimate is now saying is that
it's a method of estimating the parameters of a statistical model given the distributions
uh sorry given the observations so what we have we have here our model we were just defined what
we care about is the theta these are our model parameters um and now we have a bunch of
observations from our data right and what we would like to do now is we would like to find the parameters
that maximize the likelihood of making the observations given the parameters right so in
other words we want to make sure the model predicts what our observations say right that's
basically what it says so we would like to make sure that we're finding these parameters and in
a mathematical sense what that means is we would like to make sure we maximize the likelihood
that's why it's called maximize likelihood that the model matches whatever the true observations
are going to say
and since we're assuming right now this is a stochastic process this is why it's an estimate
and it's a likelihood estimate okay um now there's a couple of assumptions what we're making here
um and there's basically two two main assumptions
um so what we're assuming is that the maximum likelihood estimate assumes that the training
samples are independent and they're generated all by the same probability distribution we'll later
talk about which distribution is independent and they're generated all by the same probability
distribution it is but they're independent and they're from the same distribution and that's
important this is our assumptions what we're making with our maximum likelihood estimate
and assuming we say these are independent and this is very important now because assuming they're
independent for the sampling strategy this means all we have to do is we check our model we make
a prediction here basically every time that means we can simply multiply all of these predictions
from our model in other words none of the predictions have anything to do with each other
from a probabilistic standpoint right that's why we're assuming the samples that we're drawing from
our model right now they're independent and they're generated by the same probability distribution
okay so this is what we're assuming and now what we would like to do is we would like to go from
this abstract notion of please maximize the likelihood that my model matches
my model and that's what we're assuming and now what we would like to do is we would like to go
from this abstract notion of please maximize the likelihood that my model matches my observations
i would like to derive a loss function i would like to figure out how can we go from this
function here or from from this kind of abstract maximum likelihood estimate how can we go to a
loss function that we can then actually optimize in order to find the optimal parameters such that
our model is actually having the right status in order to match the observations with the highest
probability okay
so how do we do this well we want to simplify this term a little bit here and the big problem
what we're going to have here well let's call it a problem for now but we will find a solution
obviously um is this product this product makes this art max here kind of nasty to optimize when
if you're thinking about how you would optimize that it's not that straightforward but there's a
simple simple thing what we can do um so what we're going to do right now is we're going to go ahead
and just drawing the
logarithm so well looks strange right so what we're doing is we are basically going ahead and
saying here we have a product and here we have a sum but we have a sum of logarithms and this is
the nice thing about the the logarithmic property um if we're having a log a times b it's the same
as log a plus log b and you might say well okay that's fair so if you drew the logarithm
here um then you could do that but now you introduce just randomly logarithm in order
then to make this product here a sum but the trick here is that this is the logarithm is a
monotonic function so if we took the logarithm versus not the logarithm like the the monotony
is not violated because we we still have the highest probability of making the right prediction
or like to make the right prediction of the respective observations
this is a monotonic function we can very easily just draw the logarithm here and then rewrite this
product here as a sum right it's nothing complicated it's just applying this logarithmic
property and the reason why we can draw the logarithm is because this is a monotonic function
and the reason why we want to do that is this simplifies the whole problem quite a bit
like mathematically speaking if you're now going back to our linear regression
um and now what we can do is we can write this
as a sum instead of a um instead of a product um now we can actually look at what distributions
um or what probability distributions can our model have and this is our second assumption
what we're now making right now is we're saying well all of our models that we're doing
um following or all of our observations what we're what we're what we're looking at
they all fall follow a gaussian a gaussian distribution
so what shape does our probability distribution have well we're assuming it's gaussian
so assuming this is a normal distribution here um we having certain observations these are our y i's
right we're having our input features times our model parameters and we're having um the variance
here the standard deviation squared um and now what we can do is we can simply uh pull out the
mean here right so like here we have zero as our mean and we'll be pulling the mean out
and we're assuming this is our gaussian
so it's one over the square root of two pi um times sigma squared times e
to the power of minus one over two sigma squared times y i minus mu squared and we're assuming that
our y i's are drawn from this specific distribution right um and what we care about right now is we
would like to figure out what this term is here in the top what is the respective probability well
that's the thing where we can now go ahead and take this assumption
uh so what we've done here before right we have our our likelihood um and now what we can do is
we can simply go ahead and take this gaussian distribution and for this mu we're just feeding
in our xi theta right so all they're doing right now is we're simply assuming that our
our predictions our probabilities here they're gonna follow this gaussian distribution right so
all we're doing right now is we're just putting in our xi times theta we're putting this one into
our probabilities right now now right so you might say well okay this makes the term pretty
complicated but there's a little bit of an advantage where we just had because if we go
into our actual optimization problem we now know we don't have actual probabilities here we have
lot probabilities right so what we're trying to do here is we're saying our max over the sum of the
log probabilities from our model so now what we want to do is we want to put this one here back
into here and we're taking the logarithm of this whole gaussian here and this is a nice property
about the logarithm that this simplifies the whole problem quite a bit so the first thing what's going
to happen is so all i'm doing here right now is i'm putting this one into here this is my first
row here the first thing you're going to see is well okay we're taking the logarithm here
of this gaussian so
there's an e function right so the logarithm and the e function cancel out that's why the
logarithm is a pretty good choice here why we did this actually in the first place and then
the next thing what we can do is after so well first after we did that we will see here we
ending up with one constant here at the front so this one is two pi times sigma squared but
there's no x and no theta in here so there's no input and no model parameter in here the only
parameters are here um and then what we can do is we can just rewrite this whole thing as a matrix
and then this term already becomes a lot simpler right so now we have this constant here at the
beginning uh that's just a constant and now here we're having uh one over two sigma squared times
this uh well you guessed it it's a it's the same formula what we had before right it's
only the regression formula basically um okay and that's all we have right here
now right um so now what we want to do is if we want to have this log likelihood and we want to
have our r max here we're ending up with this formula how can we find the estimate of theta
well we've done this already we're setting we're looking for a linear least squares problem here
where we're setting the gradient to zero then we're ending up with our linear least squares
formulation and we try and solve that and then we're having our estimate for our maximum
likelihood estimate right so this is kind of a very important thing in machine learning that we
can kind of use this logarithm trick um in order to go from our maximum likelihood estimate um back
to our linear regression and using the same trick to solve it which is just the linear solve at the
end of the day okay um there will be some details here in the exercise session specifically regarding
the math i hope you could still follow it if it's a problem pause the video and go back and have a
look at the exercises first before you continue on the next one
so let's continue from here um but as a summary what we have been doing here um the maximum
likelihood estimator corresponds to the least squares estimate we've just derived that um
however of course we have to assume these assumptions right we had the assumptions that
our samples are drawn independent um and that they actually follow a quotient distribution
these were the two things and they're all the same distribution of course
um but what's important right now what we have done is we actually made quite a bit
of progress because now we have had an intro of linear regression and we had an intro of maximum
likelihood now we also have the concept of a loss function uh we have talked a little bit about
optimization to obtain the best model for regression um and we can do simple predictions
right now like the temperature in a room um but what we haven't talked too much about right now is
we haven't talked about our original task
our original task is this image classification task um and now the question is can we actually
do the same trick here also for classification right um so i wanted to reiterate the problem
statement here um i know some of the things here are redundant and i mentioned it already a little
bit between the slides so the regression versus the classification the difference here is very
obvious the the the difference is the regression predicts a continuous output like the temperature
of the room like you have a floating point value right whereas the classification predicts a
discrete value like a label um we can have a binary classifier like output is either zero one
or we can have a multi-class classification which is a set of n classes
right we're going to have a look at binary classification right now this is the the thing
that is well the next easy thing to look at um we're not going to talk too much about multi-class
classification today
in the next lecture um but this one is i think we want to now go from linear regression to the
analog of well i guess linear classification would be the main thing but it's it's not quite as simple
anymore and we want to talk about why it's not as simple anymore the whole method that we're going
to try to introduce here is called logistic regression and there's a reason why quote unquote
linear regression doesn't work that well for classification instead we have to do something
slightly different
this is what logistic regression is doing um so if we are starting with our linear classifier
what we would love to do is we would love to predict a probability we would like to make sure
which probability is it is it this class or is it that class now i mentioned this before a simple
way to approach this is we could just say well we do a linear regression and if my value is above
0.5 then it's class one
if it's below 0.5 then it's class 0. now the problem with that is there's nothing in our
linear regression that guarantees us that this value will between 0 and 1 and this is what we're
going to do right now we're going to simply go ahead and do a linear regression which is this
one here this linear regression here is doing nothing else x 0 times theta 0 x 1 times theta 1
x 2 times theta 2 sums it all up same thing as before
right so we have each feature vectors multiplied with one scalar technically we have we have a
we have a bias here at some point too it's a little inconsistent please forgive me about
that i but i wanted to make it a little bit easier from a from a writing perspective
and this is a score function right now
and we want to we want to just simply feed this output here into a sigmoid and this sigmoid of x
is 1 over 1 plus e to the power of minus x and the property of this function this function looks
like this so the point is that this function is between 0 and 1. it's never going to be 0
it's asymptotically approaching 0 and it's asymptotically approaching 1 right and the
idea of that is basically that we are squashing the output here between 0 and 1 such that we can
interpret it as a probability right and this is kind of convenient when it comes to classification
for instance if we're having a very high outlier here like if this linear classifier would predict
a very high outlier here it would simply squash it to 1. if it has a very low outlier it would
simply squash it to 0 and that is for classification a very desired property as we shall see
okay so what does it mean well um here for instance we
have the pro the way you would write this is what's the probability of my output being one
um for given input x given my model parameters data right that's what we couldn't scare about
like what's the probability that this is the one here um and a small spoiler alert here this is
basically a one-layer neural network right it's not a deep network um but it's a one-layer neural
network um and this is the reason why this is a one-layer neural network um and this is the reason why
we first started with linear regression and now we're going to logistic regression where we have
the sigma in it as well um i don't want to talk too much about neural networks yet but i obviously
wanted to give the hint that later when we go into neural networks and you
miss something go back to this slide here and check out um how the logistic regression works okay
right so this is logistic regression so how does it work in practice well now what we're
going to do is we would like to have the output to be a probability and what we'd like to do is
we would like to connect this to our maximum likelihood estimate what we had done before
so the probability of our output here um is now defined as follows right so what we're doing is
um following our logistic uh our maximum likelihood estimator what we had done before um
what is the question
what is the probability that all the labels are going to be predicted one
like what we care about is everything is going to be predicted one
here we have the product of all of our independent prediction here we have our model parameters here
we have our inputs and here we have the output labels equal to one and now what we do here is
we know that this model here that we have is defined as follows we know that our model
is the prediction of a sigmoid so this here is nothing else as a prediction of a sigmoid
so y hat i which is the respective prediction of this one thing here
is actually the sigmoid of this linear model here of x i theta
again be careful i'm simplifying this a little bit there's also a bias in it in practice right
so you want to want to also go to this one um and but now what we can do is we can actually go ahead
and reformulate this
similar as we have done it before and we can use a bernoulli trial
so the idea here is that this this prediction here um this phi to the power of z
times one minus phi to the power of one minus z this is nothing else but a model for coins right
so give me this input right what's the respective prediction here
z could be either zero or one this is the respective output in this case it was one but it
could be zero as well
and now what we know is we can just take this formula here for our model of the coin predictions
because this like again this is nothing else but rolling a coin over and over and over again
and defeating this one into the model of the coins all right so now what we're doing again
go back here oops we're taking this formula here and we're just putting this one into here
um so now y hat is nothing else but the product of the predictions of the sigmoid
all right this one here this y hat i is the sigmoid um this is the respective label of
our coin predictions again this is this is the model what we have used here
um and this is the negative part of it right so this is one minus again what the output prediction
is going to be to the power of one minus the other label and this one here this y i and one minus y i
is respectively the true
label could be zero for the first class or it could be one for the second class
okay um so now we're doing the same thing what we have done for our maximum likelihood estimate
uh we would like to simplify this uh formulation of probabilities uh this is all probability of
our binary output and what we would like to do is we would like to reformulate it such that
we are obtaining a loss function so again to clarify you might ask why on earth are we doing
this why on earth are we doing this well the whole point is here is if simply if you can find it so you
are doing it so again to clarify you might ask why on earth are we doing this well the whole point
is here is that you have the 10 bigidad invalidity eliminate all needed degrees Zent fehl,
we want to go ahead and get from a probability of a binary output we want to go ahead to our
loss function and this is what we're doing right now right so now we have this one we're taking
our maximum likelihood estimate and as we remember my maximum likely estimate is arc max of log p
y from x and theta and what we would like to do is we would like to make sure we get the maximum
likelihood estimate here right so we would like to maximize these probabilities okay so now here
we have our log of p here's our p now we're putting this one into here and that's what's
going to happen here so here's again our p now we're putting it into this log formulation
we can do the same trick what we have done before we have this product here of our
independent predictions now we have the sum of our log predictions and then we're simplifying
this whole thing a little bit and we're going to do the same thing here and then we're going to
do the same thing again and then we're simplifying this whole thing a little bit and then we're going
little bit because the log function and exponential function can be simplified right so we can move
this y and 1 minus y i we can move this respectively forward um and um yeah and then this is what we're
getting here right so we have here y i which is our label times the log of our y hat i this is
our sigmoid prediction uh plus 1 minus y i again it's our label uh times log 1 minus y hat i okay
there's one little thing um what kind of is relevant right so here's a minus where does
this minus come from well the point is here this probability here comes from the log likelihood
from the maximum likelihood estimator um here we would like to maximize the
function and we would like to maximize the function here so we would like to maximize
the function and we would like to maximize the function and this would be the maximum
whereas here we would like to minimize the loss function, right?
We go in here from our prediction of our probabilities,
we go in here back to our loss function, right?
So we want to derive a loss that maximizes the probabilities,
but the loss itself we want to minimize,
and this is why we needed this minus here.
Okay.
Right.
And now what we're doing is this is basically our loss function right now.
So our loss function here is now dependent on the true labels
and the sigma predictions.
So we have minus open brackets yi times log y hat i
plus 1 minus yi times log 1 minus y hat i.
Now, what do we know here?
Well, what we want to do here is basically we want to see
what happens if our label is 1.
Like, why does this happen?
Does it actually work what we're doing here?
So if our ground truth label is 1,
that means this term here will be 0, right?
So this term cancels out,
and our loss will simply be the loss of y hat i in 1 is simply log yi.
Sorry, there's the minus missing.
This minus must be here as well.
And then what we can do again,
we can go ahead and say, well, we can prove that this is true, right?
Right.
So what we want to do is we want to maximize the argmax of thetas
such that this is the maximum likelihood estimator, right?
Or to say differently, we want log y hat to be large
since the logarithm is a monotonically increasing function.
And because of that, we also want to be y hat i to be large, right?
So if this one is large, then this one is, sorry,
if this one is large, then this one is large and vice versa.
And this is the maximum likelihood estimator.
The thing that's important here is actually that one is actually the largest value of our model's estimate that it can take.
Why?
Well, we have a sigmoid function.
That's the whole point of it, right?
And if we're doing it the other way around, we're setting this one to zero,
then this one cancels out because this one will be zero.
Only this one will remain.
And then our loss function will be this one here.
I apologize for this mistake.
There must be a minus here, right?
This minus here should be here as well, respectively.
Okay.
Now, if you're putting these two things together,
this is our loss function.
We know that it can be summarized like that
because we just done the differentiation between the minus and,
sorry, the zero label case and the one label case.
And this is something what's called the binary cross entropy loss.
It's called the BCE loss, right?
And this is something that we will see very, very many times in this lecture.
We will also use the same loss in neural network land and later also expand it to the multi-class loss,
which is called softmax.
So you will see this also a couple of times.
Now, how do we actually define our cost function?
Well, now we have to go ahead and sum all of this stuff up here.
And in practice, what this means is we take this loss function, we just sum it up.
Okay.
Everywhere over all the samples, we have n samples and then there's a little one over in here.
Technically speaking, if we would be really precise,
we would also have had this one over in here in this loss function here as well,
because that's part of the maximum likelihood estimate, right?
So each sample is part of a distribution and this distribution is multiplied with the respective probability
appearing as part of the entire distribution.
So this is the entirety of the samples.
But I simplified this a little bit because I wanted to make my notation easier.
So just take it as we just averaging here over the individual loss values from each of the samples.
Okay.
What we do, well, we're minimizing our cost function.
We minimizing that one.
This is our minimization.
And again, as a brief reminder, y hat i is sigmoid of x i times theta, linear part, nonlinear part.
Okay.
Now we're going to see already we have to optimize that, right?
So now we have to also, again, optimize for our theta.
And we will already see that this theta here is part of a sigmoid right now,
which unfortunately makes this whole problem a little bit more intense to optimize.
So there's no closed-form solution anymore.
So we need to use an iterative method how to solve it.
And this iterative method is gradient descent.
Gradient descent, again,
we will talk about this a little bit in the exercises.
If you don't know it,
you should really look it up.
This is really critical.
A lot of this stuff will be based on gradient descent, what we're doing here.
And this is going to be very, very, very critical.
There will be
a little bit of more in the lecture as well.
We're going to talk about different solvers.
The one thing
what I wanted to mention here at this point, though,
is that gradient descent
is actually
or gradient-based optimization
to begin with,
is really key
to a lot of the machine learning methods.
There's also a philosophical question is
does machine learning
or this learning-based
life, in a sense,
or human life,
do we learn based on gradients?
I don't want to make the connection all the time,
but I think this was kind of a remarkable question
of how do
physical neurons actually optimize?
Because the assumption was
they are similar in a sense.
This is not so clear yet.
But what we can tell is that all neural networks
are gradient-based, and so far
specific gradient-based
optimizations
have shown really remarkable progress.
And that's what we're going to build on.
And I think that is
pretty cool and pretty exciting.
So, if we're summarizing today's
lecture, I think
the reason, I mean, I'm really excited
about all of this, because I think
obviously machine learning is really cool.
The idea is kind of we learn
from experience, right? So we're giving it more data,
and we don't have to deal with like
hand-drafting a lot of stuff anymore.
But we're learning from experiences
and can then kind of make
well, somewhat intelligent
predictions.
And to infer
something about the future. And I think this is really
useful for a lot of different tasks.
It could be very simple tasks,
and to be
pretty frank, a lot of the problems
you can actually solve with linear regression.
Like, linear regression is a
really powerful tool that you
can apply for many, many problem
statements, and they are probably
pretty good. So if a linear regressor
well, a linear regressor
should always be a good baseline, you should try first.
So,
in linear models, for instance
in complex phenomena, like weather
or so, can actually be quite good.
And
there are certain reasons why that is the case.
We're going to talk about this a little bit.
Neural networks are always the best choice,
but nowadays with a couple
of iterations now,
yeah, we have seen
the neural networks, we can tweak them quite well as well.
And that's really exciting,
but I hope as a summary
maybe of this lecture, like really take away
what machine learning has,
take away that machine learning is always
the very same concept. Namely,
you're going to go ahead,
you take a training data set,
from this training data set, you're going to fit a model
to it, you're trying to approximate the
distribution of a training set, and you
hope it's going to generalize to some answer.
It's always the same thing.
Now, of course, the devil here is in the detail.
Like, what's your model? What's your optimizer?
What's your data?
How do you optimize it well?
How do you regularize it?
There's going to be a lot of details we have to talk about
how to make this work well. And people have struggled with this
over the last five or
well, four decades basically
to get it to work to a reasonable level.
And I'm sure there's also going to be new stuff coming up.
But the backbone of all of this
is math and statistics.
And that makes it pretty exciting,
because it's on one hand quite theoretical,
but it's also very applied.
And you can actually show super, super
cool results here.
Okay, with that, I'm going to end this lecture.
In the next exercise session,
we're going to talk about the math recap part two.
I mentioned this already here
a couple of times as part of this lecture.
If anything is unclear,
please ask in the Piazza forum
or, I mean,
both ideally,
definitely watch the math recaps
and attend the math recaps.
In the next lecture,
we're going to talk about
the first neural networks,
we're going to talk about computational graphs,
and we're going to expand on what we have learned today.
A few references for further reading.
Generally speaking,
maybe I'll start at the bottom here.
General machine learning.
This lecture is not necessarily
the focus of machine learning to begin with.
But I wanted to still explain
the main concepts.
We're leaving a lot of other machine learning methods
out there.
I'm not going to talk too much about
things like support vector machines
or random decision forests.
They're also very important.
But that's not the main focus right now.
They're different models.
They have their own strengths.
One recommendation is
if you're interested in machine learning,
look at this book by Chris Bishop.
That's a very, very powerful book
generally speaking to learn
certain math concepts.
In this lecture,
in the book, they explain much better.
The other thing,
I wanted to talk a little bit about this one,
but I cut it out of the lecture itself,
was how to split training
validation and test sets
and how to make use of that.
There's a concept called cross-validation.
I would recommend having a look at this one too
because that helps you to find better hyperparameters.
It might not be
directly relevant
right away for the linear models,
but when you start
training your personal networks,
these things are actually quite useful
to know because they're actually going to help you
to get better results on your maths.
All right.
With that, we're going to be finished today.
Thanks a lot for attending
and I hope to see you for the next lecture.
Thanks everybody for joining.